Ruth Clifford Engs papers, 1947-2010 C404
Indiana University Archives
Ruth Clifford Engs papers
1947-2015
1970-2002
Indiana University Archives
Engs, Ruth Clifford (1939-09-15-)
C404
22 cubic feet 24 boxes
Ruth C. Engs served as a professor of applied health sciences at Indiana University, joining the faculty in 1973 and retiring with emeritus status in 2003. Her main areas of research included the study of the determinants of drinking behavior, especially that of university students, and the study of the role of alcohol in society in cross-cultural and historical contexts. The Ruth C. Engs papers contain documentation on her scholastic career, including files related to research, publications, and professional activities. The collection also contains subject correspondence, teaching files, personal and administrative files, and audiovisual and computer media.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers. Restricted files have been identified as such in the finding aid and have been relocated to separate boxes at the end of the collection.
Advance notice required for access.
Biographical Note
Ruth Clifford Engs was born Ruth Clifford on September 15, 1939 in Ridgway, Pennsylvania to Elinor and Theodore Alexander Clifford and was later raised in Bethel, Vermont. In 1957, she graduated from Cushing Academy in Ashburnham, Massachusetts and then enrolled at the University of Vermont in Burlington, where, in 1961, she earned a B.A. in Liberal Arts with a major in chemistry and minors in English literature and biology.
After working as a laboratory assistant to virologist Elmer Pfefferkorn at Harvard Medical School from 1961 to 1963, Engs moved briefly to Australia where she worked as a computer programmer, before moving on to San Francisco, California in July of 1964. In 1968, she earned her degree in nursing from Merritt College in Oakland Hills, California and in 1970, she received M.S.'s in both Counseling Psychology and Health Education from the University of Oregon. After earning these degrees, Ruth Engs moved to Halifax, Nova Scotia where she served as an assistant professor at Dalhousie University, teaching both health education and nursing courses for a year.
In 1973, she earned her Ed.D. in Community Health Education from the University of Tennessee, completing a dissertation entitled The personality traits and health knowledge of crisis intervention volunteers in the state of Tennessee. Degree in hand, she joined the Indiana University faculty as an assistant professor in the Department of Health and Safety Education in the School of Health, Physical Education and Recreation. In 1979, she was promoted to the rank of associate professor in the Department of Applied Health Sciences, and in 1990, she received a promotion to full professor in this department.
Ruth Engs' initial research focused on exploring factors for the determinants of university student drinking behavior. During the 1970s and 1980s, she conducted research and produced significant scholarship related to this area of concentration, and frequently collaborated with David Hanson at the State University of New York, Potsdam. She also published several textbooks during this period, including Responsible Drug and Alcohol Use (1979), Alcohol and Other Drugs: Self Responsibility (1987), and Teaching Health Education in the Elementary School, which she co-authored with Molly Wantz.
She led a committee that developed and produced a thirteen-minute alcohol education film entitled Booze and Yous (1975), and later, Drinking and Thinking (1985). Engs also developed the influential Student Alcohol Questionnaire which is still used today to measure college students' drinking behaviors and knowledge of alcohol. From 1976 to 1988, she served as the director of the Annual Drug and Alcohol Workshop at Indiana University.
Dr. Engs' later scholarship shifted focus, as she took an interest in studying the role of alcohol in society in cross-cultural and historical contexts. As a result of her research into the history of health reform in America, Engs published Clean Living Movement: American Cycles of Health Reform in 2000 and later, The Progressive Era Health Reform Movement: A Historical Dictionary in 2003. Engs' interest in the study of views of health in a historical context also led to her publication of The Eugenics Movement: An Encyclopedia in 2005. In 2008, her book Unseen Upton Sinclair explored the previously unpublished writings of author and reformer Upton Sinclair.
In addition to her published scholarship, Engs also taught Introduction to Health Counseling, Research Methods, Theories of Addictive Behaviors, Personal Health, and Epidemiology and Human Diseases. Aside from her work at Indiana University, from 1989 to 1995 Engs served as an adjunct faculty member at the Union Institute in Cincinnati, Ohio, developing an undergraduate alcohol and treatment curriculum. From 1999 to 2000, she also served as an adjunct faculty member for Walden University, for which she developed a distance learning curriculum for an introductory public health course. Throughout most of the 1980s, Dr. Engs operated a private stress reduction and self-hypnosis practice.
In 2003, Ruth Engs retired with the title of Professor Emeritus of Applied Health Science.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Research, writing and professional activities files, Correspondence files, Teaching files, Tenure and administrative files, Personal materials, Audiovisual and Removable Media, and The Saint Meinrad Archabbey Projects. The collection has been arranged based upon the original organization of the papers as received from Ruth Engs.
Scope and Content Note
The Ruth C. Engs papers have been organized into seven main series: Research, writing and professional activities files: Correspondence; Teaching files; Tenure and administrative files; Personal materials, Audiovisual and Removable Media and The Saint Meinrad Archabbey Projects.
The Research, writing and professional activities series is by far the largest in the collection, containing material that documents Dr. Engs' research, scholarship, publications, and participation in professional organizations and activities. This series includes several subseries, based largely on her original arrangement of the papers. The first several subseries document Dr. Engs' research activities, including files that contain questionnaires, surveys, and data used to support her scholarship. Another subseries contains drafts and correspondence related to articles she has written and research she has conducted. The subseries dedicated to clippings contains copies of newspaper and magazine articles that reference Engs' scholarship; clippings are organized either by specific scholarly work or by general time frame.
Subsequent subseries, including Opinions and Editorials; Published Essays and Articles; Published Research Articles; Dissertation & Master's Thesis, Essays, Encyclopedia Entries and Pedagogical Publications; Non-Research Presentations; Research Conference Presentations; Published Books and Book Chapters; Book Files; and General Book and Publication Files contain copies of scholarly work produced by Engs. Files may also include correspondence, drafts, notes, and reviews related to a work of scholarship or a presentation. Similar material related to unpublished or incomplete research can be found in the subseries titled Unpublished Handouts; Unpublished or Not Accepted Essays or Op-Eds; Unpublished or Not Accepted Research Articles/Book Chapters/Books; Unaccepted Book Proposals; and Not Started or Incomplete Research.
The Conference Programs and Proceedings subseries contains printed programs, proceedings, and other materials related to professional conferences attended by Engs. The Original Artwork, Photographs, and Illustrations subseries contains visual materials created, designed, or used by Engs in publications over the course of her professional career. The Service Committees and Projects subseries contains material documenting her participation in professional organizations. The Grant Proposals and Award Submissions subseries contains documentation related to the preparation of proposals for grants and awards. The subseries entitled Workshop Presentation & Outline Files contains materials related to workshop presentations designed and given by Ruth Engs. Finally, the Reviews Written by Ruth Engs subseries contains copies of reviews written by Engs on other individuals' scholarly contributions.
The second series, Correspondence files, consists of correspondence files maintained by Engs during her academic career and is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or subject. A set of correspondence files organized generally by decade can be found in the General Correspondence files within this series. Prominent correspondents include David Hanson, Frank McCloskey, and Dennis Daniels.
Teaching files is the third series of the collection and contains Prof. Engs' teaching materials, including syllabi, handouts, exam materials, visual materials, slides, and notes. The series contains four subseries, with each subseries devoted to teaching materials from Indiana University, the US Army Reserves, the Union Institute, and Walden University. The Indiana University subseries, which is by far the largest, contains general teaching materials, as well as teaching materials organized by course. Courses include Personal Health, Human Diseases and Epidemiology, Nature of Addictive Behaviors, and Introduction to Health Counseling. The subseries for the US Army Reserves, the Union Institute, and Walden University all contain a small quantity of general teaching and curriculum files.
The fourth series, Tenure and administrative files, contains records relating to tenure and other administrative activities during Engs' career. Included are tenure and promotion evaluations as well as CVs, annual reports, and sabbatical applications. Many of the files in this series are closed to researchers at this time.
The fifth series, Personal materials, includes photographs, writings from her early life, and biographical materials and clippings.
The sixth series, Audiovisual and Removable Media, includes recordings of lectures given by Dr. Engs and several copies of her film Booze and Yous.
The seventh and final series, The Saint Meinrad Archabbey Projects, includes two subseries. Booklets, Essays, and Drafts contains materials regarding the history of the Archabbey and finding aids created by Eng. Conversations in the Abbey contains transcripts, drafts, essays, biographies of the monks of the Order of Saint Benedict (OSB), and other materials relating to her book.
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IU Scholarworks: https://scholarworks.iu.edu/
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
Acquisition Information
97/014, 2003/056, and 2007/082.
Provenance
The bulk of the papers were gifted to the Archives by Dr. Engs in 1997, 2003, and 2007.
Appraisal
Duplicate copies of books and other publications were removed from the collection and returned to the donor.
Eugenics --Research.; College students --Alcohol use --Research.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Applied Health Science -- Faculty -- Archives; Engs, Ruth Clifford (1939-09-15-) -- Archives; Engs, Ruth Clifford (1939-09-15-) -- Correspondence
- Research, writing and professional activities files, 1963-2015; undated (Box 1)
  - Questionnaire files, 1970-2014; undated (Box 1)
    - Development of Student Alcohol Questionnaire (SAQ), 1974, 1981, 1991 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes coding from tape and materials from Engs' doctoral dissertation.
    - Development of Code Dependency Checklist, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Development of Health and Life Style Questionnaire, 1991‑1992 (Box 1)
    - The Health Concern Questionnaire, 1970-1997 (Box 1)
    - Student Health Questionnaire – Data Collected, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Alcohol Attitude Scale, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Health and Life Style Questionnaire, (Student Health Questionnaire), 1991 (Box 1)
    - Co-dependency (C.O.D.E.) Questionnaire – Feelings Checklist, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Student Intervention Checklist, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Early Codependency Data Collection, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Common Attitudes Questionnaire, undated (Box 1)
    - Student Alcohol Questionnaire, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Student Alcohol Questionnaire, Development, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Student Alcohol Questionnaire, Answers, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Student Alcohol Questionnaire, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Student Alcohol Questionnaire – Instructions for extracting and comparing data, 1971-1982 (Box 1)
      Includes examples of computer punch cards.
    - Questionnaire used for H363 Data Collection, late 1980s (Box 1)
      - 1987 (Box 1)
      - 1991 (Box 1)
      - 1994 (Box 1)
      - Alcohol Attitude Questionnaire, 1995 (Box 1)
      - 1997 (Box 1)
    - Queensland Student Drug and Alcohol Questionnaire, 1980 (Box 1)
    - UK Version of the Queensland Alcohol and Drug Questionnaire, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Ontario Lifestyle, Alcohol, and Drug Questionnaire, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Vietnamese translation, 2014 (Box 1)
    - Directions for reading data, July 2021 (Box 1)
    - Chinese translation, undated (Box 1)
    - Polish translation, undated (Box 1)
    - Spanish translation, undated (Box 1)
    - Hungarian translation, undated (Box 1)
  - National Survey of College Student Drinking files, 1982-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Returned Letters, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Alcohol Knowledge Among College Students, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - Data, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Letters, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Working File, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Data, 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - IU Sample -, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - General Data-Based Study Files, 1974-2003 (Box 1)
    - Alcohol and physical activity study, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Drinking age comparisons, 1974-1984 (Box 1)
    - Canadian (Ontario) alcohol and drug Study, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Israel and USA alcohol study, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Family background of alcoholism study (co‑dependency), 1988 (Box 1)
    - Polish drinking study (Box 1)
      - Results, 1989‑1990 (Box 1)
      - Charts, 1989‑1990 (Box 1)
    - Alcohol and illness study, 1992 (Box 1)
    - China alcohol and health study, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Scottish study, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
      - 1994 (Box 1)
      - Data, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Key, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Tables, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
      - Comparison of Scottish and USA students, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Drafts and Correspondence Related to Research, 1973-2015 (Box 2)
    - Characteristics of community mental health volunteers & "The health knowledge of volunteers in crisis intervention centers, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - The drinking behavior of college students and cognitive effects of a voluntary alcohol education program, 1978 (Box 2)
    - The drug use patterns of helping‑professional students in Brisbane, Australia, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Again ‑ let's look before we leap: the effect of physical activity on drinking and smoking patterns, 1981 (Box 2)
    - The drug taking patterns of health professional students in Brisbane, 1981 (Box 2)
    - The drug taking patterns of medical, nursing, and pharmacy students in Brisbane, Australia, 1981 (Box 2)
    - The drinking patterns and attitudes towards alcoholism of female tertiary helping professional studies in Brisbane, Australia, 1981 (Box 2)
    - The drinking patterns and drinking problems of college students, 1983 (Box 2)
    - A survey of drug use and attitudes towards alcoholism of law students and police trainees in Queensland, Australia, 1983 (Box 2)
    - The health concerns of college students and the implications for alcohol education, 1983 (Box 2)
    - College student drinking attitudes: 1970‑1982, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Correlates of alcohol knowledge among college students: 1983-1985, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Correlates of drinking problems among collegians, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Age-specific alcohol prohibition and college students' drinking problem, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Religion and collegiate drinking problems over time, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Alcohol, tobacco, caffeine and other drug patterns of nursing students in the Tayside Region of Scotland, 1987 (Box 2)
    - 7th and 8th Grade book chapters on alcohol, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Controversies in the Addictions Field, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Trends in College Students' Drinking Problems since 1982, 1988 (Box 2)
    - University student drinking patterns and problems: examining the effect of raising the purchase age, 1988 (Box 2)
    - The alcohol knowledge and drinking myths of a national sample of college students, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Testing reactance theory with a nationwide sample of college students: implications for college alcohol education programming using the health belief model, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Gender differences in drinking patterns and problems among college students: A review of the literature, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Co-dependent status and alcohol consumption among college students: An unexpected finding, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Influence of religion and culture in drinking behaviors, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Minimum age laws for alcohol beverages: Effects on consumption and traffic safety, 1990 (Box 2)
    - The Presence or absence of Roman influence on drinking patterns: A model to explain differences in Western society, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Drinking patterns of American and Polish university students: Cross‑national study, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Responders vs. non‑responders to a mail survey: are they different?, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Drinking games and problems related to alcohol among sample of college students, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Boozing & brawling on the campus: A national study of violence on campus related to drinking, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Tables used for 1990's publications and presentations, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Association of Alcohol Consumption with self reported illness among a sample of college students", 1995 (Box 2)
    - Do traditional Western European drinking practices have origins in antiquity?, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Mass Hysteria or Toxic Fumes? A case study for University Administrators, 1996 (Box 2)
    - The drinking patterns and problems of a national sample of college students, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Cycles of social reform: Is the current anti-alcohol movement cresting?, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Construct validity and the Re‑assessment of the Reliability of the Health concern Questionnaire, 1997 (Box 2)
    - The drinking behaviors of a sample of university students in Nanning, Guangxi Province, People's Republic of China, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Correlates of Alcohol, Tobacco and Marijuana Use Among Scottish University Students, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Effects of religion and religiosity on Drug Use Among a Select Sample of Scottish post‑Secondary Students, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Reduction of consumption theory: A test using the drinking patterns and problems of collegians in the United States,1983‑1995, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Youthful drinking: The making of deviant behavior, 1999 (Box 2)
    - College students, alcohol, and rape: some demographic patterns. In O'Bierek, G.M. and Obierck, S.A., 2002 (Box 2)
    - Drinking practices and patterns among collegians, 2002 (Box 2)
    - A pilot study of a school-based multimedia smoking prevention intervention for middle-school youth, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Should the drinking age be lowered, 2005-2012 (Box 2)
    - Blood pressure in Encyclopedia of Wellness, 2010 (Box 2)
    - Europe, Southern in Sage Encyclopedia, 2010 (Box 2)
    - Corsets and girdles of the Model A era, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Webb-Kenton Act in Sage Encyclopedia, 2013 (Box 2)
    - A cross sectional study of drinking patterns, prelicensure nursing education, and professional identity formation, 2014 (Box 2)
    - College students' health, drinking and smoking patterns: what has changed in 20 years?, 2014 (Box 2)
    - Differences in Drinking Patterns between female nursing and non-nursing students, 2014 (Box 2)
    - The Myth of Race, 2014 (Box 2)
    - MacMillan Diary draft, 2015 (Box 2)
  - Clippings Related to Research, 1973-2014 (Box 2a)
    - Women and Alcohol, 1984 (Box 2a)
    - Drinking and Driving, 1985 (Box 2a)
    - Age 21 Drinking Laws, 1986 (Box 2a)
    - Drinking Laws – Effect on College Students, 1987 (Box 2a)
    - Rutgers – Alcohol Abuse, 1988 (Box 2a)
    - Family Talk about Drinking Program, 1989 (Box 2a)
    - Drinking Study Results Debated, 1989 (Box 2a)
    - Clean Living Movement, 1991 (Box 2a)
    - Health Issues, 1991 (Box 2a)
    - Anti-drinking Policies and Fraternities, 1992 (Box 2a)
    - The Age of Drinking, 1992 (Box 2a)
    - Alcohol and Heart Health, 1992 (Box 2a)
    - Drinking Games, 1993 (Box 2a)
    - Drinking and College Students, 1994 (Box 2a)
    - IU researcher disputes drinking epidemic claim, 1994 (Box 2a)
    - Epidemic of heavy campus drinking is a myth: researcher, 1994 (Box 2a)
    - Tradition on the Wane: College Drinking, 1995 (Box 2a)
    - Don't make alcohol a forbidden fruit, 1995 (Box 2a)
    - IU experts differ on anti-tobacco plan, 1996 (Box 2a)
    - Wine benefits women's health, IU professor finds, 1996 (Box 2a)
    - Expert: Anti-Alcohol Ads May Promote Abuse, 1996 (Box 2a)
    - Healthy living backlash, 1997 (Box 2a)
    - How long can the anti-alcohol movement last?, 1997 (Box 2a)
    - In Vino Veritas, 1997 (Box 2a)
    - Expert on 'Clean Living Movements' Warns that Prohibitions Haven't Worked in the Past, 1998 (Box 2a)
    - The Futile Crackdown – The New Puritans, 1999 (Box 2a)
    - Clean living book, 2000 (Box 2a)
    - Assorted News Clippings, 1970s-2003 (Box 2a)
      - References to Ruth Engs' Research, 1976-2000 (Box 2a)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970s–1980s (Box 2a)
      - Miscellaneous, 1990s–2003 (Box 2a)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 2003 (Box 2a)
    - Shopping Addict, 2005 (Box 2a)
    - Shopping Addict, 2012 (Box 2a)
    - Meadowood Retirement, 2014 (Box 2a)
  - Opinions and Editorials, 1988-2015 (Box 3)
    - Are college students learning about alcohol? –, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Test identifies co-dependent traits –, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Government in danger of repeating past mistakes –, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Students big drinkers since the middle ages –, 1991 (Box 3)
    - The two political correctness movements –, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Abstain from alcohol? No, drink moderately –, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Moderate Alcohol Drinking is Better than Abstinence –, (Early 1990's) (Box 3)
    - Apology Unnecessary –, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Opposition to anti-smoking legislation –, (Mid 1990's) (Box 3)
    - We're repeating mistakes of history with new anti-tobacco legislation -, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Should the legal drinking age be lowered to 18 or 19? –, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Relieved that Indiana won't Embarrass Again –, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Working out on a hangover could speed up your recovery –, 2015 (Box 3)
  - Published Essays and Articles, 1971-2014 (Box 3)
    - So you think you want to turn on your students to health and physical education?, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Setting up a free clinic for transient youth, 1972 (Box 3)
    - What are your personal health concerns?, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Experience is the best teacher, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Peer pressure, 1975 (Box 3)
    - The School Health Program in the Soviet Union, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Alcohol Awareness for College Students, 1976 (Box 3)
    - About Yourself, 1976 (Box 3)
    - The Teenager and Alcohol, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Social Change and Educational Outcomes, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Responsibility and Alcohol, 1981 (Box 3)